<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief relation of the state of New England from the beginning of that plantation to this present year, 1689 in a letter to a person of quality.</title>
            <author>Mather, Increase, 1639-1723.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50190</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1189</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3614</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13674801</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13674801</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101219</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50190)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101219)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 794:32)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief relation of the state of New England from the beginning of that plantation to this present year, 1689 in a letter to a person of quality.</title>
                  <author>Mather, Increase, 1639-1723.</author>
                  <author>Kick, Abraham. To Her Royal Highness the Princess of Orange.</author>
                  <author>Mather, Increase, 1639-1723. De successu Evangelii apud Indos in Nova-Anglia epistola. English.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>18, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Baldwine ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Increase Mather.  Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>What is evidently a first draft of the above, containing about one-half of the text, is among the Hutchinson papers in possession of the Massachusetts Historical Society, and was printed in its collections, 3rd ser., v. 1, p. 93-101; the handwriting is not that of Mather.</note>
                  <note>The "Brief relation" includes in addition the 12th article of the Declaration of the gentlemen, merchants, and inhabitants of Boston, Apr. 18, 1689 (believed to have been written by Mather); Abraham Kick's letter to the Princess of Orange, Feb. 1, 1689 n.s.; and a translation of Mather's "De successu Evangelij apud Indos in Nova-Anglia epistola. Ad ... Johannem Leusaenum."  It was reprinted in Force's Tracts, v. 4, no. 11, and Andros tracts, v. 2, p. 147-170, the latter containing a discussion of authorship.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. [1-2]</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>New England --  History --  Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101219:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101219:1"/>
            <p>A BRIEF RELATION OF THE STATE OF New England, From the Beginning
of that PLANTATION To this Preſent Year, 1689.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In a Letter to a Perſon of Quality.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LICENCED, <hi>July</hi> 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 1689.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwine,</hi> near the
<hi>Black Bull</hi> in the <hi>Old-Baily,</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:101219:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:101219:2"/>
            <head>A BRIEF RELATION OF THE STATE OF New England.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>HONO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RED SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have received yours, wherein you deſire me to give you a Brief
Account of the paſt and preſent State of <hi>New Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which in as
few words as I can, and as ſtraits of time will permit me, I ſhall
endeavour your Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>New England</hi> contains that Tract of Land which is between
forty and forty five Degrees of Northern Latitude; It was for ſome time known
by the name of the <hi>Northern Plantation;</hi> but King <hi>Charles</hi> the
Firſt (then Prince of <hi>Wales</hi>) gave it the name of <hi>New
England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt ſettlement of the Engliſh there, was in the year
1620, <hi>viz.</hi> at <hi>New Plymouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>New England</hi> differs from other Foreign Plantations, in
reſpect of the Grounds and Motives, inducing the Firſt Planters to remove
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101219:3"/>into that <hi>American</hi> Deſert; other Plantations were
built upon Worldly Intereſts, <hi>New England</hi> upon that which is purely
Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious; for although they did, and do agree (as is evident from their
Printed Confeſſion of Faith) with all other <hi>Protestant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
Churches;</hi> and more eſpecially with <hi>England,</hi> in Matters of
Doctrin, and in all Fundamental Points of Faith; yet as to the Liturgy,
Ceremonies, and Church-Government by Biſhops, they were, and are
<hi>Non-conformiſts:</hi> It was grievous to them to think of living in
continual difference with their Proteſtant Brethren in <hi>England;</hi> upon
which account they reſolved on a peaceable SECESSION into a corner of the
World; and being deſirous to be under the Protection of <hi>England,</hi>
about twenty worthy Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men obtained a Charter from King <hi>Charles</hi>
the Firſt, bearing date from the year 1628. which giveth them Right to the
Soil, for they hold their Titles of Lands, as of the Mannor of
<hi>Eaſt-Greenwich</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> and in Common SOCAGE, which,
notwithſtanding, they purchaſed their Lands of the Indians, who were the
Native Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietors: By their mentioned Charter, they are Empower'd to Elect
yearly their own Governor, and Deputy-Governor, and Magiſtrates, as here in
<hi>London,</hi> and in other Towns Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, the Freemen chuſe their Lord
Mayors, Mayors, Aldermen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They have alſo Power to make ſuch Laws, as ſhall be moſt
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and ſuitable for the Plantation: Nevertheleſs, as an
acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of <hi>their dependance on England,</hi> by their Charters,
they are obliged not to make any Laws, which ſhall be repugnant to the Laws
in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo, the fifth part of all <hi>Oar,</hi> of Gold or Silver,
found in that Territory, belongs to the Crown of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Report of this Charter, did encourage many very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving
perſons to Tranſplant themſelves, and their Families, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>New
England;</hi> Gentlemen of Ancient and Worſhipful Families, and Miniſters
of the Goſpel, then of great fame here in <hi>England,</hi> Tradeſmen,
Artificers, and Planters, to the Number of about four thouſand did in twelve
years time go thither.</p>
            <p>The hazards they run, and the difficulties which they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred
with, in ſubduing a Wilderneſs, cannot be eaſily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt in a large
Tract: But the Almighty God, by a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Providence, carried them through
all.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:101219:3"/>In the year 1637, they were in imminent danger
of being cut off by the barbarous Heathen; but when it came to a War, mighty
numbers of the Indians were ſlain, by a few of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, which cauſed
a terror of God to fall upon the Heathen round about; ſo that after the
<hi>Pequod</hi> Indians were ſubdued, there was peace in the Land for forty
eight years together; and being ſetled under a good and eaſie Government,
the Plantation in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, and proſpered wonderfully; yea, ſo as cannot
be pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallelled in any Hiſtory: never was place brought to ſuch a
Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderableneſs in ſo ſhort a time; that which was, not long ſince,
a howling Wilderneſs, in few years time, became a pleaſant Land, wherein
was abundance of all things meet for Soul and Body, which can be imputed to
nothing elſe, but to their Religion, the Goſpel bringing a fulneſs of
Bleſſings along with it: Some have obſerved, that ſince the year 1640,
more Perſons have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved out of <hi>New England,</hi> than have gone
thither. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, the four thouſand, who did, between that and the
year 1620, tranſplant themſelves into <hi>New England,</hi> are ſo
mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velouſly increaſed, as that, if the Computation fail not, they are now
become more than Two hundred thouſand Souls.</p>
            <p>There are Towns and Villages, on the Sea-Coaſts, from <hi>Long
Iſland</hi> to <hi>Boſton,</hi> which is Three hundred Engliſh Miles, and
the like from <hi>Boſton</hi> to <hi>Pemmaquid,</hi> which is Two hundred
Miles more.</p>
            <p>In the year 1662, <hi>Conecticot</hi> Colony, as alſo <hi>Read
Iſland,</hi> with the Plantations thereunto belonging, had Charters granted
to them by King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, being much of the ſame Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor
with the Patent of the <hi>Maſſachuſets,</hi> whereby theſe Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonies
were made diſtinct Government.</p>
            <p>In the year 1675, the Indians began a ſecond War with the
Engliſh; the Iſſue of which was, that whole Nations of them were
deſtroy'd.</p>
            <p>Never did men ſhew greater Courage and Bravery in their
En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters with the Barbarous Heathen, than they did. Although it muſt be
acknowledged that the <hi>Indians</hi> advantages were ſuch, as they could
not have been overcome, if God had not fought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, by ſending the
Evil Arrows of Famine, and Mortal Diſeaſes among them. I have often thought
of an Expreſſion of<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101219:4"/>an Indian there: <hi>We could eaſily
be too hard for the Engliſh, but</hi> (ſaid he? ſtriking on his Breaſt)
<hi>The Engliſhmens God makes us afraid here.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As long as they enjoyed their firſt Government, no Enemies could
ſtand before them; but ſince that they have not been able to ſubdue an
hundred Indians, who did the laſt year commit ſome outrages among them,
having been (as I am credibly inſormed) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignedly provoked thereunto by
ſome Injuries done unto them by thoſe then in Power, who intended the Ruine
of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, and Advancement of the French Intereſt in that
Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory.</p>
            <p>As for your Enquiry, <hi>By what means they came to be deprived of
their Charters, Rights and Liberties;</hi> pleaſe to underſtand, that in
the year 1683, a <hi>Quo Warranto</hi> was iſſued out againſt them, and
with the Notification thereof by the then King's Order there was a Declaration
publiſhed, enjoyning thoſe few particular Perſons men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the
<hi>Quo Warranto,</hi> to make their defence at their own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Charge,
without any help by a publick Stock: By this it was eaſie to ſee that
ſome Perſons were reſolv'd to have the Charters condemned, <hi>quo jure
quaque injuria:</hi> Nevertheleſs, the Governor and Company appointed an
Attorney to appear, and anſwer to the <hi>Quo Warranto,</hi> in the Court of
King's Bench.</p>
            <p>The Proſecutors not being able to make any thing of it there, a
new Suit was Commenced by a <hi>Scire facias,</hi> in the High Court of
Chancery.</p>
            <p>But tho they had not ſufficient time given them to make their
Defence, yet Judgment was entred againſt them for Default in not appearing;
when it was impoſſible, conſidering the remote diſtance of <hi>New
England</hi> from <hi>Westminſter-hall,</hi> that they ſhould appear in the
time allowed.</p>
            <p>Thus illegally was the Charter of the <hi>Maſſachuſets</hi>
Colony wreſted from them: as for the Colonies of <hi>Plymouth,
Conecticot,</hi> and <hi>Road Iſland,</hi> there was never any Judgment
againſt them, nor any Surrender; but by a mere Rape, in the year 1686, their
Charters and Priviledges were violently taken from them.</p>
            <p>Since that time the Country hath mightily declined, and gone to
ruin daily, not being now like the place it was Five Years ago, which is not
much to be wondred at, conſidering the Intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101219:4"/>Oppreſſions they have been Labouring under, ſince their Charters
were Raviſhed from them.</p>
            <p>In the Year 1686. <hi>Sir Edmond Andros,</hi> was ſent by the
late King <hi>James</hi> to <hi>New England;</hi> with a Commiſſion
abſolutely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to the fundamentals of the <hi>Engliſh</hi>
Government, Impow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ering him with Four more (none of them choſen by the
People) to Levy Money, and make Laws, nay, and in caſe of War in the
Plantations to ſend as many of the Inhabitants as he would, two Thouſand
Miles out of the Country: This Commiſſion being Illegal and ſo in it
ſelf void, the People not being able to Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue longer under thoſe
Oppreſſions, did this laſt Spring aſſert their Engliſh Liberties,
Rights and Priviledges, and Unanimouſly Declare for <hi>the Prince of Orange,
and the Parliament of England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it is greatly to be obſerved, that as long as <hi>New
England</hi> enjoyed their Charters for more than Fifty Years together, they
never put the Crown of <hi>England</hi> to a Penny Charge; which is more than
can be ſaid of any other Forreign Plantations depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant on
<hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſince they have been under a Government not by
<hi>Charters,</hi> but by <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> the Country hath been
Chargeable, and leſs Beneficial to the Kings Revenue than in former
times.</p>
            <p>It hath indeed been objected, that in <hi>New England</hi> they
did many Years a go Tranſgreſs <hi>the Act of Navigation.</hi> But the
Traſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſome few particular Perſons ought not to be charged
as the fault of the Government there, who did in the Year 1663, make a Law that
the Act of Navigation ſhould be Strictly obſerved, and their Governours are
Sworn to ſee that Law Executed, and have to the uttermoſt of their power
been careful therein.</p>
            <p>Many other Things have been ſuggeſted againſt <hi>New
England,</hi> he moſt of which having no footſteps of Truth in them, but
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Malicious Inventions of the <hi>Tobijahs</hi> and
<hi>Sanballats</hi> of the Age, are not worth mentioning.</p>
            <p>Not but the People there being but Men, have had their failings as
well as other Men in all places of the World. The only thing (ſo far as I can
learn) which can with any Coluor of Truth be juſtly reflected on them as a
great fault, is that in ſome matters relating to Conſcience and difference
of opinion, they have been more rigid and ſevere than the Primitive
Chriſtians or the Goſpel doth allow of.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:101219:5"/>Yet this is to be ſaid in their behalf, that
things are reported worſe than indeed they were, and that now many Leading
Men, and the generality of the People are of a more moderate Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
            <p>I know many that have a great Intereſt there, do abhor the
Spirit of Perſecution as much as any Men in the World.</p>
            <p>It is certainly for the Intereſt of <hi>England,</hi> that
<hi>New England</hi> be incouraged; and preſerved in all their Rights,
Priviledges and Properties, and thoſe ill Men who have given or ſhall give
contrary advice (notwithſtanding all their vain pretences to the contrary)
have and will prejudice the Intereſt of the Crown more than they are, or ever
were, or can be able to make amends for: which I evince by the Arguments
following.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. The Kings Revenue, all things conſidered, is as much or
more augmented by <hi>New England,</hi> than by any other of the Foreign
Plantations. This will ſeem to ſome a ſtrange Aſſertion: But
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what I ſay, and then judge if it be not true.
<p>The other <hi>American Plantations</hi> cannot well
ſubſiſt without <hi>New England;</hi> which is by a Thouſand Leagues
nearer to them than either <hi>England,</hi> or <hi>Ireland;</hi> ſo that
they are ſupplied with Proviſions, Beef, Pork, Meal, Fiſh, &amp;c. And
alſo with the Lumber Trade, Deal Boards, Pipe-Staves, &amp;c. chiefly from
<hi>New England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Alſo the <hi>Carribbe Iſlands</hi> have theire Horſes
from thence. It is then in a greater part by means of <hi>New England</hi> that
the other Plantations are made proſperous and beneficial; they pay Cuſtoms
in the Plantations for the Goods they Export from thence into <hi>New
England,</hi> and when thoſe Goods are brought into <hi>England,</hi> they
pay the ſame again the Second time, by which means not a little is
contributed to the Crown.</p>
                  <p>Some Manufactures there are amongſt them, but not a
Twenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth part of what the Country hath need of, or is conſumed there,
moſt of their Cloathing as to Woollen and Linnen, all ſorts of Upholſtery
Wares, Haberdaſhers and Silk Wares, Stuffs, Silks, &amp;c. they have from
<hi>England;</hi> and make returns in Plate, Pieces of Eight, Beaver, Mooſe
and Deer Skins, Oyl, and Iron, all which, but the Bullion, the Country
affords.</p>
                  <p>Alſo by Sugars and Tobacco, Indico, and indeed all the
Product<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101219:5"/>of the other Plantations, which with their own
Veſſels they fetch and tranſport to <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
               </item>
               <item>II. I know not whether in the World there be a better place
for ſhipping, nor can I ſay how many, (but many hundreds there are)
hundreds of Veſſels of their own building do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the Country,
(beſides great Numbers built and ſold into <hi>England,</hi>) for they
yearly build many good Ships, ſome of which for <hi>London,</hi> and other
places in <hi>England.</hi>
                  <p>The Country abounds with Pine-Trees, Excellent Cedars, and Oak
for building of Ships, and Ship-Maſts in abundance; by thoſe that are
proper Judges, the beſt in the World, and come yearly from thence for the
Uſe of the King's Ships.</p>
                  <p>And it hath been affirmed by knowing Men in Navigation and
Building, that whenever the King of <hi>England</hi> pleaſes, he may in
<hi>New England</hi> on ſuch eaſie Rates as is ſcarce imaginable, build
Navies of Ships: There being no better Timber in the World, and in ſuch
quantities as are inexhauſtible, and in ſuch convenient Places, as if God
and Nature had adapted theſe vaſt Timbers for the ſaid uſe; which is
worth conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, for that Timber is generally wanting in
<hi>England,</hi> and in <hi>Ireland;</hi> what is, is too far from Waters and
Places fit for Carriage, and the Eaſt-Land Oak is ſpungy and
unfit.</p>
               </item>
               <item>III. The Engliſh born in <hi>New England,</hi> have the
true inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Spirit of the <hi>Old,</hi> apt and fit for Martial Employs; and
as an addition to their Natural Courage and Sobriety, are well inſtructed in
Martial Diſcipline.</item>
            </list>
            <p>All the Inhabitants from ſixteen to ſixty Years in each Town,
are by the Law and conſtant Cuſtom of the Country to bear Arms, if
occaſion ſhall require, and that they may be fit ſo to do,</p>
            <p>They have in each Town and Village their Training-days, eight
Times every Year, wherein they are exerciſed in Military Diſcipline, that
ſo they may be expert in War, on all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, for their own Defence, and
Service of their Prince; who will find whenever he ſhall pleaſe for to
command, and commiſſionate them, that they are able (by the Bleſſing of
God) to ſecure and enlarge his Dominions, and to bring<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101219:6"/>their French Neighbours into an intire Subjection to the Crown of
<hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And from this Conſideration it was, that the French
Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, (who all the World knows had a mighty Aſcendent over
<hi>White-Hall,</hi> in the Two Late Kings Reigns) ceaſed not in their
Negotiations, until amongſt other Articles agreed on; One was, that in Caſe
of a War betwixt <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> there ſhall be a
Neutrality in the Plantations: They wiſely foreſeeing, that if the King of
<hi>England,</hi> ſhould arm and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion his Subjects in <hi>New
England,</hi> the Frenchmen in thoſe parts could not ſtand before them.</p>
            <p>In the Time of the Late Protector <hi>Cromwel,</hi> they did by
order from <hi>England,</hi> take ſeveral Forts from the French, which by
King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second were reſtored to them again; no ways to the
Honour or Intereſt of the Engliſh Nation.</p>
            <p>And it's hoped, His Majeſty and the High Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
will put that value upon <hi>New England,</hi> as ſo vaſt a Tract of Land
and Body of People deſerve from a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on which they depend, and are
ſo great and uſeful a Member, as they have manifeſted themſelves to be:
And that in ſo Eminent a manner as calls for Protection, Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and
Reſtauration to all their Rights, Priviledges and Proprieties, and what
Additions more, as in His Majeſty great Wiſdom, ſhall be thought fit for
his Service, the Proteſtant Religion and the good of that People; who on the
18th. of <hi>April,</hi> 1689. Unanimouſly roſe in Arms, and after having
ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed upon their Illegal Governour, and the reſt of their
Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors; declared for the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and the
Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>England,</hi> the Proteſtant Religion and their Ancient
Conſtitution, and to this day do keep the Country for our Preſent
Sovereigns, King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> againſt King
<hi>Lewis,</hi> and the Abdicated King <hi>James,</hi> waiting His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties
Commands, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which Declaration is in the words following:
<q>WE do therefore ſeize upon the Perſons of thoſe few
<hi>Ill Men,</hi> which have (been next unto our<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101219:6"/>ſins) the
Grand Authors of our Miſeries, reſolving to ſecure them, for what
Juſtice, Orders from his Highneſs, with the Engliſh Parliament ſhall
direct, leſt, e're we are aware, we find (what we may fear, being on all
ſides in danger) our ſelves to be by them given away to a Foreign
<hi>Power,</hi> before ſuch Orders can reach unto us, for which Orders we now
humbly wait; in the mean time firmly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, that we have endeavoured
nothing but what meer Duty to God and our Country calls for at our hands: We
commit our Enterprize to the <hi>Bleſſing</hi> of him, <hi>who hears the
Cry of the oppreſſed,</hi> and adviſe all our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours for whom we
have thus ventured our ſelves, to joyn with us in Prayers, and all juſt
Actions for the Defence of the Land.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The twelfth Article of <hi>New England</hi> is the Key of the
<hi>New World America;</hi> if the French King had got it into his
Poſſeſſion, he might ſoon have made himſelf Maſter of
<hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica,</hi> and this in all Probability would have been done this
Summer, if the <hi>New Englanders</hi> in and about <hi>Boſton,</hi>
pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trating into the Deſigns carrying on, had not riſen as one Man, and
ſeized Sir <hi>E. A.</hi> (who is as of a French Extract, ſo in the French
Intereſts; being ſent to <hi>New England</hi> by the Late King
<hi>James,</hi> with an Illegal and Arbitrary Commiſſion) and thoſe ill
Men who joyned with him in his Tyranny.</p>
            <p>All men do acknowledge, that thoſe brave Souls whom God hath
ſo wonderfully aſſiſted, and ſpirited to preſerve
<hi>London-Derry,</hi> (and perhaps thereby to ſave all <hi>Ireland</hi>) by
ſecuring it, and declaring for King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi>
deſerve great Favour and Protection from the Government.</p>
            <p>And the ſame muſt be acknowledged due unto the People of
<hi>New England,</hi> and more eſpecially, when it is conſidered of what
Value and Conſequence to <hi>England, New England</hi> is, and that they ſo
early as it were, reſcued the Country out of the hands of the French, even
before they knew the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was King of <hi>England,</hi>
and that at a Time when they<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101219:7"/>knew no more, than that His
Highneſs was landed in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> with a deſign to endeavour the
delivering the Kingdom, and the Churches of God from Popery, Slavery and
Arbitrary Power, which as they lookt upon as an Heroick and Glorious
Undertaking; ſo they alſo accounted it their Duty to embark themſelves in
the ſame Cauſe; though they knew not what the Iſſue of ſo mighty a
Work would be; which hath cauſed ſome Perſons of no Mean Figure to ſay,

<q>Theſe People deſerve His Majeſties and the Nations
Reſpect, Countenance, and Speedy Reſtitution of all their Rights, and to be
en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled by His Majeſties Commiſſions to proſecute the War againſt
<hi>France</hi> in <hi>America,</hi> which they are capable to do without any
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Charge to the Government.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed <hi>New England,</hi> hath upon the beſt Accounts
which can be mentioned, out-done all <hi>America.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For there they have erected an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> which
began in the year 1642, wherein things are managed, <hi>pro more Academia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum
in Anglia:</hi> Several Perſons of more than ordinary Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; yea, and
many ſcores of able Miniſters, of the Goſpel, have there had their
Education.</p>
            <p>There by the Statutes of the <hi>Colledge,</hi> none is to be
admitted, before he can write Latin in a pure Style, and tranſlate any
or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Greek Author.</p>
            <p>It is cuſtomary with them, every Morning in the Colledge-Hall,
to read a Chapter out of the Hebrew Bible, and at Night a Chapter out of the
Greek Original.</p>
            <p>The Tutors there inſtruct their Pupils in <hi>Logick, Natural
and Moral Philoſophy, Metaphyſicks, Geography, Aſtronomy, Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metick,
Geometry,</hi> &amp;c. and the Learned Men there have a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſponding
communication with other Learned Men in divers parts of the World, where the
Reformed Religion is profeſſed, and by them highly reverenced for their
Learning and Sobrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; an Inſtance of which appears by the following Letter,
written by the Eminent Mr. <hi>Kick,</hi> to the Queen's Majeſty that now is,
in <hi>February</hi> laſt, by way of Supplication for <hi>New
Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:101219:7"/>
                  <head>To Her Royal Highneſs the Princeſs of <hi>Orange,</hi>
&amp;c.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>May it pleaſe your Royal Highneſs,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THE great and good God, who
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>th foretold us in the Scriptures,
that a great and wonderful Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance ſhall be wrought for his Church in
the latter days, when <hi>the Mountain of Zion ſhall be exalted in the top of
the Mountains,</hi> ſeemeth to have deſigned to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> uſe of His Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi>
and Your Royal Highneſs, as Inſtruments in that glorious Deliverance:
Having al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready done ſuch marvellous things in <hi>England</hi> by His
High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in order to that great Work; inſomuch, that the Eyes of all the
Proteſtant Churches, and People of God, are this day towards His Highneſs,
and Your Royal Highneſs, as Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in God's Hand for the further
carrying on of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance of his Church, from the cruel Sufferings and
Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions it is under in moſt parts of World. For which reaſon I
have taken the boldneſs to become Your. Royal Highneſſes humble
Remembrancer, on the behalf of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and Church of God in <hi>New
England:</hi> Who about Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty years ſince forſook their own Native
Country, and went into that howling Wilderneſs, that they might enjoy the
Liberty of their Conſciences in the Worſhip of God. They are a People
indeed not much taken notice of, yet a People <hi>by</hi> and <hi>for</hi> whom
God hath done great things, and by whoſe aſſiſtance the Engliſh
Colonies and Plantations in <hi>Ameri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> and the <hi>Weſt-India</hi>
Iſlands may be much profited; and in caſe of War with <hi>France,</hi> many
of the French Colonies, in thoſe parts, may be reduced to the Obedience and
Intereſt of the Engliſh Nation. They have erected a <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, that hath produced very many able Divines,<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101219:8"/>who have been very Inſtrumental in the Converſion of many, of the
Indians, to the Chriſtian Faith, having for the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of that good
Work, Tranſlated the Bible into the Indian Tongue</p>
                  <p>Their Confeſſion of Faith and Church-Diſcipline, I have
made bold to preſent to Your Royal Highneſs, that you may ſee they are
Orthodox. This People had a Patent granted them by King <hi>James,</hi> to
chooſe their own Governors, and to make their own Laws, (not repugnant to the
Laws of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>) wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
Patent was Ratified to them by King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt and Second,
and ſo continued until the late ill Mode of <hi>Quo Warranto</hi>'s came up,
and that they had one ſent to them about their Patent. For the defending of
which, they ſtood a Tryal at <hi>Weſtminſter-hall,</hi> and caſt the
King; but the King cauſed it to be brought to a Review, and by Stratagems
uſed then in ſuch like Caſes, forced a Judgment againſt the ſaid
Patent; and thereupon took away all their Priviledges, and Impoſed a
Governor, and new Laws upon them, which they exceedingly much groan under. And
although I am ſatisfied, that ſo ſoon as they ſhall come to hear of the
great and wonderful things that God hath done in <hi>England</hi> by His
Highneſs, for the Reſtoring of Charters and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, they will then
Addreſs themſelves to Your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, ſeeking the Reſtoration of
theirs; yet in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard they are ſo many thouſand Miles diſtant, it will
be long e're it come to their knowledge.</p>
                  <p>Therefore I have adventured on their behalf (having had a
Correſpondency with the ſaid People many years, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how much they
will ſuffer, if their new Governor be not ſpeedily removed) to give Your
Royal Highneſs the trouble of theſe Lines, praying to God that He will
pleaſe to move your Heart to take the Firſt opportunity to help them to the
Reſtoration of their Ancient Patent, Priviledges and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties: That they
and all the Churches of God may have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101219:8"/>to own His
Highneſs, and Your Royal Highneſs, as Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of their Breaches, and
Reſtorers of Paths to dwell in: And to rejoyce in the Goodneſs of God in
fulfilling that Promiſe, of making <hi>Kings</hi> to be <hi>Nurſing
Fathers,</hi> and <hi>Queens</hi> to be <hi>Nurſing Mothers</hi> to his
Church. I humbly beg your Royal Highneſſes Pardon for the trouble of
theſe Lines, and take leave to ſubſcribe my ſelf,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>GREAT MADAM,</salute> 
                     <signed>Your Royal Highneſſes Moſt Obedient and Moſt
humble Servant <hi>ABRAHAM KICK.</hi>
                     </signed> 
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Hague</hi> 
                        <date>the Firſt of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary,</hi> 1689. S.
N.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Nay, I will be bold to ſay, that <hi>New England</hi> hath
out-done the whole World; for among the Indians, who a while ſince were mere
Heathens, there are not only many Congregations of them, who are converted to
the Chriſtian Faith, and the Proteſtant (which is the only True) Religion:
But no leſs than Four and twenty of thoſe Heathens, are now not only
Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, but Preachers of the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt. And I
chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge the whole World to produce me the like Inſtance, as more fully
appears by the following Relation, abſtracted out of a Letter written about
two years ſince from <hi>Boſton,</hi> by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Mr. <hi>Mather,</hi>
Preſident of the College there, at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, and unto the famous Dr.
<hi>John Leuſden,</hi> Hebrew Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor in the Univerſity of
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tricht,</hi> and ſince tranſlated into di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Languages in <hi>New
England.</hi> The whole Bible hath been tranſlated into the Indian Language,
and there alſo printed: It's above forty five years ſince, that truly pious
and godly Man, Mr. <hi>John Elliot,</hi> Miniſter of the Church at
<hi>Rocksborough</hi> (a Mile from <hi>Boſton</hi>) being warm'd with a
Compaſſionate and Holy Zeal for the Converſion of the <hi>Americans,</hi>
ſet himſelf to learn the<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101219:9"/>Indian Tongue, that he might the
more eaſily, and ſucceſsfully open to them the Myſteries of the
Goſpel; on account of which he hath been (not undeſervedly) called <hi>the
Apostle of the Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rican Indians.</hi> This Reverend Perſon was he that, with
indefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigable Labour and Study, tranſlated the whole Bible into the Indian
Tongue, and alſo ſeveral Engliſh Treatiſes of Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Divinity and
Catechiſms.</p>
            <p>About Twenty eight years ſince he gathered a Church of Converted
Indians, in a Town called <hi>Natick.</hi> Theſe poor In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians were brought
to ſuch a ſenſe of God and Religion, that they confeſſed their Sins
with Tears, and profeſſed their Faith in Chriſt; and afterwards they and
their Children were Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, and they were Solemnly joyned together in a
Church-Covenant: And Mr. <hi>Elliot</hi> was the firſt that Adminiſtred the
Lords Supper to them. The Miniſter of that Church is now an Indian named
<hi>Daniel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides this Church at <hi>Natick,</hi> among our Inhabitants in
the Maſſachuſets Colony, there are Four <hi>Indian</hi> Aſſemblies;
where the Name of the True God, and Jeſus Chriſt, is ſolemnly called
upon. And theſe Four Aſſemblies have American Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: Mr.
<hi>Elliot</hi> formerly Preached to them once in Fourteen Days; but now being
Weakned with his Labours, and in the Eighty Sixth Year of his Age, doth not
Preach to them more than once in Two Months.</p>
            <p>About Fifty Miles from <hi>Boſton</hi> is another Church
conſiſting only of Converted Indians; in an Indian Town, called
<hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippang,</hi> the firſt Miniſter of which was an Engliſhman,
who being skilful in the <hi>American Language,</hi> Preached the Goſpel to
them in their own Tongue; but this Miniſter is lately Dead, and they now have
an Indian Preacher.</p>
            <p>There are beſides that, Five Aſſemblies of Indians
profeſſing the Name of Chriſt, not far diſtant from
<hi>Marſhippang,</hi> which have Indian Preachers, and alſo are Preached
unto in their own Language once every weak by Mr. <hi>John Cotton,</hi> Son of
the Famous Mr. <hi>John Cotton,</hi> ſomtimes Miniſter of the Church at
<hi>Boſton.</hi> In <hi>Plymouth</hi> Colony of the Inhabitants of
<hi>Saconet</hi> there is a great Congregation of thoſe who for
diſtinctions ſake, are called <hi>Praying Indians;</hi> Becauſe they Pray
to God in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:101219:9"/>Not far from a Promontory called <hi>Cape
Cod,</hi> are Six Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of Heathens who are to be reckoned as
<hi>Catechumeni;</hi> amongſt whom are Six Indian Preachers. Mr. <hi>Samuel
Treat</hi> Miniſter of a Church at <hi>Eaſt Ham,</hi> Preacheth to theſe
Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations in their own Language.</p>
            <p>There are amongſt the Iſlanders of <hi>Mantucket,</hi> a
Church, with a Miniſter who was lately a Heathen, and ſeveral meetings of
<hi>Catechumeni,</hi> who are inſtructed by the Converted Indians.</p>
            <p>In the Iſland of <hi>Martha,</hi> which is about Twenty Two
Miles long, are two American Churches planted, which are more Famous than the
reſt, for that over one of them preſides an Ancient Indian Miniſter,
called <hi>Hiacooms: John Hiacooms,</hi> Son of the ſaid Indian Miniſter,
alſo Preaches the Goſpel to his Contrymen in
<gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> Church: in that place <hi>John
Tockinoſh,</hi> a Converted Indian Teaches.</p>
            <p>In theſe Churches <hi>Ruling Elders</hi> of the Indians are
joyned to the Miniſters: The Miniſters were choſen by the People, and
when they had Faſted and Prayed, Mr. <hi>Elliott</hi> and Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi>
laid their hands on them, ſo that they were ſolemnly Ordained.</p>
            <p>All the Congregations of the Converted Indians, (the
<hi>Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chumeni</hi> and thoſe that are in Church-Order) every Lords Day
meet together, the Miniſter always beginning with Prayer, and without a Form,
becauſe from the heart; when the Ruler of the Aſſembly hath ended his
Prayer, the whole Cogregation of Indians, praiſe God with Singing; in which
many of them are excelling. After the Pſalm, he that Preaches reads a place
of Scripture, and Expounds it, gathers Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrins from it, proves them by
Scripture and reaſons, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers uſe from them after the manner of the
Engliſh, of whom they have been taught: Then another Prayer to God in the
Name of Chriſt concludes the whole Service, in which man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner they meet twice
every Lord's Day; they obſerve no Holy Days, but the Lord's Day, except upon
ſome extraordinary occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; and then they ſolemnly ſet apart whole
Days, either in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thanks, or faſting and praying with great fervor of
Mind.</p>
            <p>Before the Engliſh came into theſe Parts, theſe Barbarous
Nations were altogether ignorant of the true God; hence it is, that in their
Prayers and Sermons, they uſe Engliſh Words and Terms.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:101219:10"/>He that calls upon the moſt Holy Name of
God, ſays, <hi>Jehovah,</hi> or God, or Lord; and alſo they have Learned,
and borrowed many other Theological Phraſes from the Engliſh.</p>
            <p>There are ſix Churches of Baptized Indians in <hi>New
England,</hi> and eighteen Aſſemblies of <hi>Catechumeni,</hi>
profeſſing the Name of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Of the Indians there are four and twenty who are Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the
Word of God, and there are alſo four Engliſh Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters who Preach the
Goſpel in the Indian Tongue, and there are many of the Indians Children, who
have learned by heart the Catechiſm; either of that ſamous Divine Mr.
<hi>Will. Perkins,</hi> or that put forth by the Aſſembly of Divines at
<hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> and can in their own Mother-Tongue anſwer to all
the queſtions in it.</p>
            <p>Thus Sir I have endeavoured to gratifie your requeſt with as
much Brevity as the Subject will admit, and exceeding the Bounds of a Letter,
am forced to be ſo prolix, and the rather for that moſt of what I have
written is upon my own knowledge, Truth (and the reſt undeniable fact) though
not the twentieth Part of the Truths might be ſaid of the Almighty's moſt
won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful bleſſing and proſpering <hi>New England,</hi> and his Goſpel
among the Heathen there, which to me looks like the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of the
fulfilling thoſe many Prophecies in <hi>Holy Writ</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them.</p>
            <p>And after all this, I cannot but admire there ſhould be (as you
ſay there is) any Man in <hi>England,</hi> who owns but even the bare name of
a Proteſtant, at ſuch a time as this, when God ſeems to have begun the
Reformation of the whole World, and eminently to appear for the True Reformed
Religion, ſhould be an Enemy unto ſuch a People as are in <hi>New
England,</hi> and their Diſcipline, as to the Religious Worſhip: When as to
all know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and unprejudiced perſons, its conſonant to the practice of the
Primitive Church, and of the Reformed Churches through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the World: Which one
would think ſhould not find an Enemy among any ſort of Chriſtians, but
thoſe called Papiſts, or elſe among ſuch, as <hi>Papiſt like</hi> can
give up their Religion, Rights, Liberties, and Properties, nay, their very
Senſes to the conduct of their Fellow Creatures.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:101219:10"/>
            <head>Books lately Printed for <hi>R. Baldwin.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>THE Hiſtory of the moſt Illuſtrious <hi>VVilliam,</hi>
Prince of <hi>Orangc:</hi> deduc'd from the firſt Founders of the Ancient
Houſe of <hi>Naſſau:</hi> Together with the moſt Conſiderable Actions
of this Preſent Prince.</item>
               <item>Fourteen Papers, viz. 1. <hi>A Letter from a Gentleman
in</hi> Ireland, <hi>to his Fri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd
in</hi> London, <hi>upon occaſion of a Pamplet, Entituled,</hi> A Vindication
of the preſent Government of <hi>reland,</hi> under his Excellency
<hi>Richard</hi> Earl of <hi>Tyrconnel.</hi> 2. <hi>A Letter from a Freeholder,
to the reſt of the Freeholders of</hi> England, <hi>and all Others, who have
Votes in the Choice of Parliament M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 3. <hi>An Enquiry into the Reaſons for Abrogating the Test
impoſed on all Members of Parliament. Offered by</hi> S. Ox. 4.
<hi>Reflections on a late Pamphlet, Entituled,</hi> Parlimentum Pacificum,
<hi>Licenſed by the Earl of</hi> Sunderland, <hi>and printed at</hi> London
<hi>in</hi> March 1688. 5. <hi>A L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tter to a Diſſenter, upon occaſion of his Majeſties Gracious
Declaration of Indulgence.</hi> 6. <hi>The Anatomy of an Equivalent.</hi> 7.
<hi>A Letter from a Clergy-man in the City, to his Friend in the Country,
containing his Reaſons for not reading the Declaration.</hi> 8. <hi>An
An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the City Miniſter's Letter, from his Country Friend.</hi> 9.
<hi>A Letter to a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter from his Friend at the</hi> Hague,
<hi>concerning the Penal Laws, and the Test; ſhewing, that the Popular Plea
for Liberty of Conſcience, is not concerned in that Queſtion.</hi> 10.
<hi>A plain Account of the Perſecution laid to the Charge of the Church
of</hi> England. 11. <hi>Abby and other Church-lands, not Aſſured to ſuch
Poſſeſſors as are</hi> Roman <hi>Catholicks; Dedicated to the Nobility
and Gentry of that Religion.</hi> 12. <hi>The King's Power in
Eccleſiaſtical matters truly Stated.</hi> 13. <hi>A Letter of
ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral</hi> French <hi>Miniſters fled into</hi> Germany <hi>upon the
account of the Perſecution in</hi> France, <hi>to ſuch of their Brethren
in</hi> England <hi>as approved the King's Declaration touching Liberty of
Conſcience. Tranſlated from the Original in French.</hi> 14. <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh
Treatiſe not to be Fely'd on: In a
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tter from a Gentleman at</hi> York,
<hi>to his Friend in the Prince of</hi> Orange<hi>'s Camp: Addreſſed to all
Members of the next Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The VVay to Peace amongſt all Proteſtants: Being a Letter
of Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation ſent by Biſhop <hi>Ridley</hi> to Biſhop
<hi>Hooper,</hi> with ſome Obſervations upon it. By <hi>Samuel
Johnſon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Purgatory prov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d
by Miracles: Collected out of <hi>Roman</hi> Catho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ick Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors. VVith ſome remarkable Hiſtories
relating to Britiſh, Engliſh and Iriſh Saints. VVith a Preface concerning
Miracles By <hi>S. Johnſon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An Hiſtorical Relation of ſeveral Great and Learned
Fomaniſts who did imbrace the Proteſtant Beligion, with their Reaſons for
their Change de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd in their own words. Collected chiefly from moſt
eminent Hiſtorians of the <hi>Roman</hi> Perſwaſion. To which is added, a
Catalogue of ſundry great Perſons of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Religion,
who have all along oppos'd the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:101219:11"/>The Character of a Trimmer: His Opinion of, 1.
The Laws and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. 2. Proteſtant Religion. 3. The Papiſts. 4.
Foreign Affairs. By the Honourable Sir <hi>W. Coventry.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Seaſonable Diſcourſe, ſhewing the
Unreaſonableneſs and Miſchiefs of Impoſitions in Matters of Religion,
recommended to ſerious Conſideration. By Mr. <hi>Andr. Marvel,</hi> a late
Member of the Honourable Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</item>
               <item>The Revolter. A Trage-Comedy acted between the <hi>Hind</hi>
and <hi>Patter,</hi> and <hi>Religio Laici,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>The Abſolute Neceſſity of Standing by the Preſent
Government: or a View of what both Church-men and Diſſenters muſt Expect,
if by their Unhappy Diviſions Popery and Tyranny ſhould return
again.</item>
               <item>An Impartial Relation of the Illegal Proceedings againſt
St. <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> Colledge in <hi>Oxon,</hi> in the Year of our Lord
1687, containing only Matters of Fact as they occurred. Collected by a Fellow
of the ſaid Colledge.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:101219:11"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
